Guide to the Theodore and Ruth Lidz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings and Research, 1936-2000; Series III
  - Lectures and other presentations
    - A theory [Department of Psychiatry research conference], 1972 (Box 24, Folder 152)
    - "The Family and a Theory of Schizophrenia" [Downstate Medical Center], 1973 (Box 24, Folder 153)
    - "The Family, Myth, and Ethics" [New Jersey Association for Mental Health, Association of Existential Psychology and Psychiatry], 1973, 1976 (Box 24, Folder 154)
    - "Family Studies and a Theory of Schizophrenia" [Stanley R. Dean Award, American College of Psychiatrists], 1973 (Box 24, Folder 155)
    - New Guinea paper [Johns Hopkins], 1973 (Box 24, Folder 156)
    - Rosen, Victor H., [eulogy], 1973 (Box 24, Folder 157)
    - Schizophrenic disorders theory [Philadelphia], 1973 (Box 24, Folder 158)
    - "The Family: Dynamics and Treatment" [grand rounds, Butler Hospital], 1974 (Box 24, Folder 159)
    - "The Family and the Self" [P.O. C. A., Boston], 1975 (Box 24, Folder 160)
    - "Family Studies and Psychoanalytic Theory and Therapy: The Impact of Family Studies on Psychoanalysis" [American Psychiatric Association], 1975 (Box 24, Folder 161)
    - "Commentary on 'A Critical Review of Recent Adoption, Twin, and Family Studies of Schizophrenia'" [Second Rochester International Conference on Schizophrenia], 1976 (Box 24, Folder 162)
    - A theory of schizophrenic disorders, 1976 modification [Massachusetts General Hospital] (Box 24, Folder 163)
    - "Family Studies and Changing Concepts of Personality Development" [Toronto], 1978 (Box 24, Folder 164)
    - "Critique of the Danish-American Studies of the Biological and Adoptive Relatives of the Adoptees Who Became Schizophrenic" [reply to Kety's criticism], 1978] (Box 24, Folder 165)
    - "Amphetamine Addiction in Adolescent Girls" [with R.W. Lidz, family process meeting], 197- (Box 24, Folder 166)
    - Family, in etiology and treatment of psychiatric patients [Western New England Psychoanalytic Society], 197- (Box 24, Folder 167)
    - "Session on Family and Sociological Approaches" [opening and closing remarks], 197- (Box 24, Folder 168)
    - "Family Transactions and Psychoanalytic Theory" [Alfred Stanton Lecture, MacLean Hospital], 1980 (Box 25, Folder 169)
    - "An Orientation to the Study of Schizophrenic Disorders" [Cologne], 1982 (Box 25, Folder 170)
    - "The Regression of American Psychiatry" [H. S. Sullivan Memorial Lecture], 1983 (Box 25, Folder 171)
    - World Congress lecture, 1983 (Box 25, Folder 172)
    - "A Psychosocial Orientation to Schizophrenic Disorders" [Eighth International Conference on the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia], 1984 (Box 25, Folder 173)
    - Japanese psychiatric association lecture, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 174)
    - "Male Menstruation, Ritual Insemination and Masculinity in Papua New Guinea: A Psychoanalytic Perspective" [Kanzer Freud Lecture], 1985 (Box 25, Folder 175)
    - "The Family in Individual Therapy" [Heidelberg, Baton Rouge], 1985, 1987 (Box 25, Folder 176)
    - "Psychoanalysis and Schizophrenia" [Munich], 1986 (Box 25, Folder 177)
    - Masculinization in Papua New Guinea [American Academy of Psychoanalysts], 1987 (Box 25, Folder 178)
    - "The Family and Psychoanalytic Theory", 1987 (Box 25, Folder 179)
    - Second Annual Cape Cod Symposium [with R.W. Lidz], 1987
      - General, 1987 (Box 25, Folder 180)
      - "Family Transactions and the 'Choice' of the Psychiatric Syndrome", 1987 (Box 25, Folder 181)
      - "The Not So Latent Latency", 1987 (Box 25, Folder 182)
    - "Collecting Oceanic Artefacts", 1988 (Box 25, Folder 183)
    - "The Role of Chaos in the Etiology and Treatment of Schizophrenia" [Turin], 1988 (Box 25, Folder 184)
    - " Wild Strawberries by Bergman" [American Psychoanalytic Society session on Film and Dream], 1988 (Box 25, Folder 185)
    - "The Family and Psychoanalytic Theory: Problems of Adopted Children" [summary, American College of Psychoanalysts meeting], 1989 (Box 25, Folder 186)
    - Adolescent addicts and schizophrenia [Bruch conference, Houston], 198- (Box 25, Folder 187)
    - Boys' oedipal transition, 198- (Box 25, Folder 188)
    - International Conference on Schizophrenia, VIII, 198- (Box 25, Folder 189)
    - Meyer, Adolf [transcript of interview with T. Lidz by Otto Marx], 1990 (Box 25, Folder 190)
    - "Strindberg's Inferno --the Portrayal of a Schizophrenic Psychosis in a Novel" [International Symposium for the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia], 1991 (Box 25, Folder 191)
    - Session on Family and Sociocultural Approaches [opening and closing remarks], 1998 (Box 25, Folder 192)
    - Adolescence, undated (Box 25, Folder 193)
    - Amphetamine addiction, undated (Box 25, Folder 194)
    - Atkin's presentation on interrelationships between language and thought and psychoanalysis, undated (Box 25, Folder 195)
    - "The Contribution of Psychiatry to Medicine" [Chicago], undated (Box 26, Folder 196)
    - "A Developmental Concept of Schizophrenia" [Cologne], undated (Box 26, Folder 197)
    - "Draft on Hamlet, undated (Box 26, Folder 198)
    - "The Effects of Long-Term Illness on the Family" [rheumatic fever program], undated (Box 26, Folder 199)
    - Emotional factors in hyperthyroidism, undated (Box 26, Folder 200)
    - Family and schizophrenia, undated (Box 26, Folder 201)
    - "The Family as a Focus of Preventive Psychiatry" [S. Fleck retirement], undated (Box 26, Folder 202)
    - Family disorganization and schizophrenia, undated (Box 26, Folder 203)
    - Family settings produce schizophrenia [Montreal], undated (Box 26, Folder 204)
    - "Family Studies and Changing Concepts of Personality Development", undated (Box 26, Folder 205)
    - Fleck, Stephen [retirement; conference on Mental Health, Mental Illness and the Family], undated (Box 26, Folder 206)
    - Fourth international meeting on the psychoanalysis of schizophrenia [address], undated (Box 26, Folder 207)
    - Hypertension case, undated (Box 26, Folder 208)
    - "In Defense of the Family" [Mishkan Israel], undated (Box 26, Folder 209)
    - Kitay Award presentation to Jean Piaget, undated (Box 26, Folder 210)
    - Life cycle, undated (Box 26, Folder 211)
    - Loewald's "Comments on Some Instinctual Manifestations of Superego Formation", undated (Box 26, Folder 212)
    - Lubart's paper on goiter [discussion], undated (Box 26, Folder 213)
    - "New Proposal for the Education of Psychiatrists", undated (Box 26, Folder 214)
    - Origin and nature of schizophrenic disorders, undated (Box 26, Folder 215)
    - Psychiatric teaching [Yale], undated (Box 26, Folder 216)
    - The psychotherapy of schizophrenia [Heidelberg, with R. Lidz] III, undated (Box 26, Folder 217)
    - Salmon Committee on Psychiatry and Mental Hygiene [medal presentation to F. C. Redlich], undated (Box 26, Folder 218)
    - "Schizophrenic Disorders: The Influence of Conceptualization on Therapy" [with comments by O. A. Will], undated (Box 26, Folder 219)
    - Silberger's "To His Apprehensive Friend: Nathaniel Hawthorne and The Scarlet Letter, undated (Box 26, Folder 220)
    - Skinner conference, undated (Box 26, Folder 221)
    - "Study of Irreconcilable Identifications in a Borderline Case" [Western New England Psychoanalytic Society], undated (Box 26, Folder 222)
    - Ursano and Lazarus papers, undated (Box 26, Folder 223)
  - Notes and other research materials
    - Alanen's The Mothers of Schizophrenic Patients, undated (Box 27, Folder 224)
    - Family theory, 1960-1962 (Box 27, Folder 225)
    - Freud, 198- (Box 27, Folder 226)
    - Freud's Totem and Taboo, 197- (Box 27, Folder 227)
    - Hamlet, 1969-1970 (Box 27, Folder 228)
    - Language and thought in schizophrenia, undated (Box 27, Folder 229)
    - Marriage and the family, 197- (Box 27, Folder 230)
    - Nightmare, undated (Box 27, Folder 231)
    - Organic deterioration, Undated (Box 27, Folder 232)
    - Organic psychoses, undated (Box 27, Folder 233)
    - Samueli, undated (Box 27, Folder 234)
    - "Schiz.", 1996 (Box 27, Folder 235)
    - South Pacific cultures
      - General, 197- (Box 27, Folder 236)
      - Families of the South Pacific, 1971? (Box 27, Folder 237)
      - Fiji
        - Families, 1944? (Box 27, Folder 238)
        - Primitive religion, totemism, 197- (Box 27, Folder 239)
      - Papua New Guinea, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 240)
      - "Telefol Folk Stories" [collected and translated by Robert Brambaugh], 1985 (Box 27, Folder 241-242)
    - Strindberg studies, 197- (Box 27, Folder 243)
    - Strindberg's writings, 196- (Box 27, Folder 244-245)
    - Twins, 196- (Box 27, Folder 246)
    - Unidentified, 1939-197-, undated (Box 27, Folder 247)
  - Research data
    - General, 1943-1991 (Box 28, Folder 248-255)
      Closed until January 1, 2066. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - ACTH studies, 1952 (Box 28, Folder 256)
      Closed until January 1, 2027. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Age and schizophrenic studies, 1937-1939] (Box 28, Folder 257)
    - "The Amnestic Syndrome"
      - Case studies, 1938-1941 (Box 28, Folder 258-259)
        See also: Series III, Box 30, Folder 287
      - Working materials, 1939-1942 (Box 28, Folder 260)
        Closed until January 1, 2017. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Amphetamine study, 1972 (Box 28, Folder 261)
      Closed until January 1, 2047. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Analysis of pre-frontal lobe syndrome, undated (Box 28, Folder 262)
    - Atabrine, 1944 (Box 29, Folder 263)
      Closed until January 1, 2019. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Frontal lobe study, 1939-1941 (Box 29, Folder 264)
    - Hyperthyroidism: case studies, 1946-1950 (Box 29, Folder 265-270)
      Closed until January 1, 2025. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Liberated prisoners from Germany [case studies], 1944-1945 (Box 29, Folder 271)
      Closed until January 1, 2020. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Malarial studies, 1944 (Box 29, Folder 272)
    - Marriages [case summaries, by S. Schafer et. al.], 1959-1961 (Box 29, Folder 273-274)
      Closed until January 1, 2036. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Obstetrical patients, 194- (Box 30, Folder 275)
      Closed until January 1, 2024. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Patient files
      - A., M., 1978-1979 (Box 30, Folder 276)
        Closed until January 1, 2054. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - A., N., 1981 (Box 30, Folder 277)
        Closed until January 1, 2056. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - A., R., 1954 (Box 30, Folder 278)
        Closed until January 1, 2029. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - Cr... family, 198- (Box 30, Folder 279)
        Closed until January 1, 2064. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - G., T., 1957-1958 (Box 30, Folder 280)
        Closed until January 1, 2033. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - L., D., 1972 (Box 30, Folder 281)
      - Li... family, undated (Box 30, Folder 282)
      - Ma., W., 1982 (Box 30, Folder 283)
        Closed until January 1, 2057. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - Mo., J., 1991 (Box 30, Folder 284)
      - Mo., Y., 1973-1986 (Box 30, Folder 285)
        Closed until January 1, 2061. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - S., A., 1973-1981 (Box 30, Folder 286)
      - S., O. III, 1939-1941 (Box 30, Folder 287)
      - S., P., 1948-1971 (Box 30, Folder 288-292)
        Closed until January 1, 2046. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - V., E., 1976-1977 (Box 30, Folder 293)
        Closed until January 1, 2052. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Possick, Stanley [case studies], 1975 (Box 31, Folder 294-296)
      Closed until January 1, 2050. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Pregnancy and hyperthyroidism, 1948 (Box 31, Folder 297)
      Closed until January 1, 2023. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Psychopathic families, 1960-1964 (Box 31, Folder 298)
      Closed until January 1, 2039. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
    - Schizophrenia and the Family
      - General
        - "Casework Interviewing as a Research Technique in a Study of Families of Schizophrenic Patients," by Alice R. Cornelison, 1955? (Box 31, Folder 299)
          Closed until January 1, 2030. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Code names and real names, 1985 (Box 31, Folder 300)
          Closed until January 1, 2045. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
      - Families
        - Benjamin, 1954-1961 (Box 31, Folder 301-305)
        - Benjamin, 1954-1961 (Box 32, Folder 306-314)
        - Benjamin, 1954-1961 (Box 33, Folder 315-317)
        - Forel, 1953-1960, undated (Box 33, Folder 318-319)
          Closed until January 1, 2035. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Grau, 1953-1963 (Box 33, Folder 320-323)
          Closed until January 1, 2038. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Grau, 1953-1963 (Box 34, Folder 324-327)
        - Lamb, 1953-1960 (Box 34, Folder 328-337)
        - Lamb, 1953-1960 (Box 35, Folder 338)
        - Lerner, 1939-1965 (Box 35, Folder 339-348)
          Closed until January 1, 2040. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Lerner, 1939-1965 (Box 36, Folder 349-359)
        - Lerner, 1939-1965 (Box 37, Folder 360)
        - Lerner, 1939-1965 (Box 38, Folder 361)
        - Narab, 1956-1964 (Box 38, Folder 362-372)
        - Narab, 1956-1964 (Box 39, Folder 373-375)
        - Nebb, 1953-1958 (Box 39, Folder 376-384)
        - Newberg, 1954-1964 (Box 39, Folder 385)
        - Newberg, 1954-1964 (Box 40, Folder 386-393)
        - Newcomb, 1954-1960 (Box 40, Folder 394-397)
        - Newcomb, 1954-1960 (Box 41, Folder 398-401)
        - Nussbaum, 1954-1957 (Box 41, Folder 402-407)
          Closed until January 1, 2032. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Reading, 1955? (Box 42, Folder 408)
        - Robb, 1957-1960 (Box 42, Folder 409-412)
        - Sc..., 1954-1956 (Box 42, Folder 413-416)
          Closed until January 1, 2031. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Schwarz, 1953-1955 (Box 42, Folder 417-419)
        - Thomas, 1955-1963 (Box 42, Folder 420)
        - Thomas, 1955-1963 (Box 43, Folder 421-429)
        - Ubanque, 1952-1964 (Box 43, Folder 430)
        - X, 1963 (Box 43, Folder 431)
      - Schizophrenia studies
        - General, 1938-1961 (Box 44, Folder 432-434)
        - Basic data [R. Lidz and T. Lidz] III, 1936-1939 (Box 44, Folder 435)
        - Family testing [Margaret Thaler Singer], 1960-1962 (Box 44, Folder 436-441)
          Closed until January 1, 2037. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Henry Phipps Clinic cases, 1941 (Box 45, Folder 442-443)
        - Literature reviews, 1950s-1960s- (Box 45, Folder 444-448)
          Closed until January 1, 2044. Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
        - Mothers, 1950-1960 (Box 45, Folder 449-450)
        - Siblings [case summaries], 1959-1960 (Box 45, Folder 451-452)
- Teaching, 1948-1972, undated; Series IV
  The Teaching files represent only a small percentage of Lidz's teaching career and are only those materials that Theodore Lidz chose to preserve. First year medical school lectures and outlines over several years are included. The files may also contain notes, lectures, syllabi, correspondence, and discussion of curricula. Some courses at other institutions besides Yale School of Medicine and Johns Hopkins are included, specifically for institutions abroad and for the U.S. Army.
  - Fiji, 1971 (Box 46, Folder 1-2)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1947-1950 (Box 46, Folder 3-7)
  - Middletown lectures, 1962 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - United States
    - Department of the Army IV, 1948-1952 (Box 46, Folder 9)
    - Veterans Administration, 1950 (Box 46, Folder 10)
  - Walter Reed Hospital [military medicine], 1952 (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Yale University
    - Ezra Stiles seminar, 1970-1971 (Box 46, Folder 12)
    - Family integration, 1956 (Box 46, Folder 13)
    - First year medical school course
      - Proposal, 1952 (Box 46, Folder 14)
      - Lectures, 1953-1967, undated (Box 46, Folder 15-19)
      - Lectures, 1953-1967, undated (Box 47, Folder 20-24)
    - Human biology and ecology, 1951-1952 (Box 47, Folder 25)
    - Language seminar, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 26)
    - Late adolescence, early adulthood, 1954-1957 (Box 47, Folder 27)
    - Marriage-sex and marriage, pregnancy and parenthood, 1955-1956 (Box 47, Folder 28)
    - Phases of adult life, undated (Box 47, Folder 29)
    - Psychiatry 101
      - Bibliographies, syllabi, 1955-1958 (Box 47, Folder 30)
      - Lectures, 1952-1955 (Box 47, Folder 31)
    - Psychiatry 133, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 32)
    - "Psychosexual Review", 1953-1955 (Box 47, Folder 33)
    - Psychosomatic medicine, 1953-1955 (Box 47, Folder 34)
- Personal, 1927-2001; Series V
  The series contains the personal papers of Theodore Lidz. Of particular interest are the autobiographical sketches that supplement the autobiographical writings in Series III. Similar material for Ruth Lidz is in Series I, but art objects listings, memorabilia, photographs, and travels files that document interests and events in the shared life of Ruth and Theodore Lidz are included here. Memorabilia is composed of letters of appointment, press releases, and brochures for meetings at which the Lidzes gave presentations.
  - Art objects [inventory, appraisal], 1976, 1987 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Autobiographical sketches, 1927-1989 (Box 48, Folder 2-3)
  - Bibliographies, 1952- 198- (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1932-1998 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Congratulatory letters on appointment as chairman, Department of Psychiatry, 1967 (Box 48, Folder 6-7)
  - Curricula vitae, 1950s-1980s- (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Doodles, 1964, undated (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - Memorabilia, 1946-1991 (Box 48, Folder 10-11)
  - Military service, 1948-1954 (Box 48, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, 1932-1980s, undated (Box 48, Folder 13)
  - Psychoanalytic training, 1949-1954 (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - Reviews of T. Lidz papers, 1989, 1993 (Box 49, Folder 15)
  - Travels
    - Fiji, New Zealand, 1970-1971 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Africa, Brazil, 1972-1974 (Box 49, Folder 17-18)
    - Galapagos, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 19)
  - Tributes and obituaries, 1977, 2001 (Box 49, Folder 20)